Ours is truly a blue planet.
我们的地球是颗蓝色的行星
Water covers most of the world's surface.
水覆盖了大部分地球表面
Here we are the outsiders.
在这里我们是旁观者
But under the waves one group thrives.
但碧波之下，有种生物却很兴盛
Fish are masters of the waters.
鱼类是水中高手
And sailfish are the fastest of them all.
旗鱼又是所有鱼中最快的
Their speed makes them one of the ocean's most fearsome predators.
速度使它们成为海洋里最可怕的食肉动物之一
Off the coast of Mexico, 30 sailfish have surrounded a ball of sardines.
墨西哥海域，30条旗鱼包围着一群沙丁鱼
To catch their prey requires more than speed alone.
要抓到猎物，不仅仅单靠速度
In the tightest turns, fins maintain stability.
急转弯时，鱼鳍依旧结实
Their sickle-shaped tail powers them forwards
它们靠镰刀形的尾巴驱动前进
and that extraordinary dorsal fin helps intimidate their prey.
外形奇特的背鳍能够恐吓猎物
To the naked eye, the action is too fast,
肉眼看来，它们的动作太快了
slowed, their challenge becomes clear.
慢镜头下，它们的战术才清晰呈现
Just picking a target is hard enough.
选定一个目标非常困难
Knocking it off balance, separates it from the shoal.
通过敲打使它失去平衡，并将之从鱼群里孤立出来
This requires extraordinary skill.
这需要极高的技巧
Not every attempt is successful.
并非每次尝试都能成功
But as more sailfish join in, when one misses another takes its place.
但随着越来越多的旗鱼加入，一个失手，另一个迅速跟上
The shoal of sardines is methodically wiped out.
这群沙丁鱼被有条不紊地猎食殆尽
Sailfish are top predators, very little threatens them.
旗鱼是顶级猎食者，极少生物能威胁到它们
But for the majority of fish this is not the case.
对大多数的鱼类来说，不是这回事
For most fish the open ocean is extremely dangerous.
开阔的海洋对它们是极度危险的
And some go to extraordinary lengths just to survive.
有些能作出惊人之举，只为逃生
Flying fish.
飞鱼
Free of the water they soar on elongated fins,
靠超长的鳍，它们飞出水面
leaving their predators far behind.
将猎食者远远甩在后面
A flight of fish.
鱼类的飞行家
Escaping predators is not the only test facing the flying fish.
飞鱼所面临的考验，不仅仅只是逃避天敌
They must also protect their developing young.
它们也必须保护发育中的后代
These flying fish are searching for the one thing that will make this possible.
飞鱼在寻找一种特殊的东西，使之成为可能
In such a vast ocean it's not easy.
在如此辽阔的海洋里，并不容易
They're in luck.
它们很幸运
A palm frond.
一片棕榈叶
It's a tiny island adrift in a huge ocean.
海洋里漂流的微型岛屿
And like an island it offers shelter, not for the flying fish,
它可以提供庇护所，但不是为飞鱼
but for their eggs.
而是给它们的卵
The females lay eggs on the raft, where the males fertilise them.
雌鱼在叶子上产卵，雄鱼使它们受精
The first fish spawn and this triggers the others to start.
一条鱼的排卵会引发其它的鱼也开始排卵
Soon thousands join the melee.
不一会儿，成千上万条鱼参与进来
Innumerable strands of eggs are laid.
产下难以计数的卵
The raft starts to tilt under their weight.
重压之下“木筏”开始倾斜
The best place to lay eggs is right inside the frond.
最佳产卵地点在叶子的中间
For some the attempt proves fatal and living fish become entombed.
有些尝试被证明是失败的，它成了一些鱼的坟墓
The raft starts to sink under the weight of so many eggs.
在如此多鱼卵的重压下，它开始下沉
But this is far from a disaster.
但这并非灾难
Sinking away from the surface actually improves the eggs' chances of survival.
沉到水面以下，实际上可以提高鱼卵的存活机会
In just a few days, having been safely hidden in the depths,
在深处安全地躲避着，几天后
they'll hatch out.
它们全都孵化出来
Other fish protect their offspring in different ways.
其它的鱼则用不同的方式保护后代
Some go to far greater lengths to care for them.
有些在照料后代方面走的更远
The shallow waters of southern Australia
澳大利亚南部的浅水区
are home to many strange creatures.
是许多奇异生物的家园
It's a fairytale world of sea horses...
童话般的海马王国
..stargazers...
占星鱼（一直瞪着眼看天空）
..and stingrays.
鳐鱼
But none compare with the beauty of the weedy sea dragon.
但谁也比不上海藻龙的美丽
The dragon's tiny fins beat frantically
它的背鳍快速地震动
to prevent the current from sweeping it away.
防止自己被水流冲走
It's the beginning of spring,
现在是早春
the season when sea dragons begin their courtship.
海藻龙的求爱期开始了
And in the evening light, they start to dance.
在夜光下，它们开始跳舞
In a graceful duet, each partner mirrors the actions of the other.
在优美的二重奏里，一只龙能准确地模仿伴侣的动作
Darkness will soon draw a veil over the pair
夜色很快就将这一对儿笼罩
but they will dance on, into the night.
但它们会继续跳舞，直到深夜
Two months later, and the result of their courtship is revealed.
两个月后，它们的爱情结晶就会出现
It's the male and he's the one that's carrying the eggs,
雄性海藻龙，它是携带着卵的那只
with rows and rows of them embedded in his tail.
一排一排的固定在它的尾巴上
That night the female transferred her eggs to him.
那一夜，雌性将卵移交给了它
Since then, the male alone has cared for them.
从那以后，它将独自照看这些卵
By carrying them with him he's kept them safe.
这样随身带着它们可以保证安全
And now it's time for his efforts to be rewarded.
现在，是它的付出得到回报的时候了
The eggs are ready to hatch.
卵开始孵化
In the calm of a summer morning
在一个宁静的夏日早晨
a baby sea dragon, with yolk sac still attached, is born.
一个还带着卵囊小海龙诞生了
The weed bed shelters older dragons
海藻床为能够自己觅食的
that are already able to feed themselves.
成年海龙提供庇护
Although these dragons were well cared for by their father,
尽管这些小海龙从父亲那里得到了很好的照料
now they must find their own way in the world.
如今，它们必须独自寻找食物
There are fish, however,
然而，还有一种鱼
which provide their young with a safe refuge for far longer.
能够给后代提供更为长久的保护
The south western Pacific.
太平洋西南部
A convict fish
喷沙鱼（译者自命名）
and it's something of a marine architect.
它是海底的建筑师
Underground it has created a labyrinth of tunnels.
在地下制造了迷宫一样的通道
This adult never ventures out of its burrow, what it eats is a mystery.
成年鱼从来不敢从洞里出来，它吃什么仍旧是个谜
But it doesn't live here alone.
但它并非独住
At another entrance faces peer out.
另一个门口露出了许多小脸儿
Juvenile convict fish.
幼年喷沙鱼
Unlike their parent, the youngsters are not tied to the burrow.
不像成年鱼，这些小子不会被地洞所束缚
And as they start to emerge, a trickle becomes a flood of fish.
一旦它们现身，细流会变成洪水
There are thousands of them.
成千上万
And they all help with the chores.
它们都帮助做家务
Many hands make light work.
鱼多力量大
The young fish swarm together.
它们在一起游动
Thousands of mouths gulping plankton.
上万张嘴吞食食物
What the adults eat must somehow involve these youngsters.
成年鱼吃什么，应该跟这些小鱼有关
Whether the young feed their parents by regurgitating food
到底是小鱼们通过反刍来喂养大鱼呢？
or through some other mechanism, we just don't know.
还是有其它的方式，我们无从得知
Whatever the answer, the youngsters provide
无论答案如何，小鱼们给大鱼提供食物
their parents with a meal and in return get a roof over their heads.
它们的父母则提供庇护所作为回报
Producing young is just one challenge.
繁衍后代只是一个挑战
Finding food and somewhere to live are further trials fish must face.
寻找食物和居住场所，是鱼类必须面临的进一步考验
The Californian coast, a wide range of species live here.
加利福利亚海岸，生存着大量的生物
But all this life means competition for living space is intense.
这也意味着生存空间的竞争异常激烈
Old shells are highly prized.
老掉的贝壳是很宝贵的
And this one is occupied by a sarcastic fringehead.
这个壳被一个怪头鱼（译者自命名）所占据
These fish are exceptionally quarrelsome,
这种鱼非常的好斗
they have to be, to defend their living space.
它们必须保护自己的住所
An octopus.
一条章鱼
Inadvertently it's wandered into the fringehead's territory
一不小心就进入了怪头鱼的地盘
and that can't be tolerated.
这是无法容忍的
The octopus's impressive jab holds the fringehead at bay.
章鱼用特殊的腕足猛戳怪头鱼
There is more to this behaviour than being bad-tempered.
这种行为远非坏脾气所能解释
The fringehead needs to defend its patch if it is to get enough to eat
想要得到充足的食物，怪头鱼必须守住自己的场子
and the octopus was competition.
章鱼就是个对手
Crabs are not the easiest of mouthfuls.
蟹可不是那么好吞的
Because of the shortage of living space there are constant boundary disputes,
由于生存空间狭小，这里总有不间断的领土纠纷
especially with other fringeheads
特别是和另一条怪头鱼
and this one has got too close.
这家伙越界了
Despite the most extravagant threats...
尽管面对如此夸张的恐吓
..neither is prepared to back down.
它们都不打算收手
Success, and it's quick to get back to its shell.
胜利了，然后迅速回到壳里
A fringehead can never drop its guard, there's too much competition.
怪头鱼从来不会放松警惕，因为竞争者实在太多
Some fish have moved to places where they have fewer rivals.
有些鱼类则迁移到竞争相对较少的地方
A mudskipper a fish that spends most of its life out of the sea.
弹涂鱼，一生中大部分时间都在水外度过
It can walk on land and breathe air.
它能在地上爬行，呼吸空气
Its life is very different from that of most fish.
生活方式和大部分的鱼很不相同
A fish out of water maybe,
一般的鱼偶尔也会出水
but they thrive here in Japan.
但它们在日本的这个地方却很繁盛
So what's made this upheaval worthwhile?
所以，为何作出如此大的改变？
The answer lies in the mud.
答案就在泥巴里
As the tide retreats it exposes mudflats.
退潮后，暴露出一片滩涂
Sunlight hits the rich silt and tiny plants and animals flourish there.
阳光照耀在肥沃的泥土上，各种小型生物得以繁盛
All food for a mudskipper.
这些都是弹涂鱼的食物
But life on land is not without problems,
但陆上生活并非没有麻烦
it's hard work to find a mate.
很难找到配偶
Jumping high above the mud will get you noticed.
从泥滩上高高跃起，可以让自己受到关注
With eyes perched on top of their heads
弹涂鱼那双长在头顶的双眼
the mudskippers keep a look out for both friend and foe.
时刻关注着朋友，警惕着敌人
And males fight those who intrude on their territory.
雄性还会同入侵者打斗
They must also take care not to dry out in the sun.
它们也要谨防自己被晒干
Rolling in the ooze keeps the skin cool and moist.
在泥浆里打滚能够降温并且保湿
For this smaller species,
对这种小动物来说
a better option is to retreat underground.
退回地下乃是上策
So he digs himself a tunnel down into the mud.
所以它在泥巴里为自己挖好了地道
His heap of spoil is an indication of the extent of his excavations.
它洞外堆积的泥巴能显示出挖掘的深度
With the tide flooding the tunnel twice a day,
潮水会每天两次淹没地道
maintenance is a real burden.
维修工作比较繁重
The tunnel is more than a refuge from the sun,
地道不仅仅是躲避太阳的
it serves another very important purpose.
也有另一种重要的用途
The tunnel is actually U-shaped and at the far end is a sealed chamber,
地道实际上是U型的，末端有个封闭的小室
the walls of which are lined with eggs.
墙壁上布满了鱼卵
The eggs are kept in air as it's richer in oxygen than the water.
鱼卵保持露天状态，因为空气中的氧气含量比水中要高
The problem is the air that's trapped here won't last for long.
问题是这里所储存的空气支持不了多久
So the male travels to the open end of the tunnel to gulp fresh air.
所以雄鱼会游到洞口，吞下新鲜空气
Back he goes down his tunnel where he releases it into the egg chamber.
再潜回地道将空气吐到孵卵小室里
Replenishing the oxygen on which the eggs depend.
补充卵孵化所需的氧气
He will repeat this hundreds and hundreds of times until his young hatch.
它会一次又一次地重复这个过程，直到后代孵化出来
This lifestyle is very demanding,
尽管这种生活方式很辛苦
yet the mudskipper has found a way around every problem.
弹涂鱼还是能设法解决每一个问题
The harsh challenges of life in the ocean
海洋里严酷的生活挑战
have encouraged other fish to leave the sea.
也迫使另一种鱼离开了大海
Not for land, but for fresh water.
不是去到陆地，而是淡水
Hawaii is the remotest island chain on the planet.
夏威夷是地球上最偏远的群岛
These pools look the perfect place for a fish to live,
这溪流看起来是个鱼类生存的好地方
secluded and free from competition and predators.
独立，没什么竞争和猎食者
Yet few contain fish, for one very considerable reason.
但这里很少有鱼，一个很大的原因是
Surely no fish could swim up this.
没有鱼能上游到这里来
But one fish comes from the ocean, intent on colonising these streams.
但有一种来自海洋的鱼，下决心要移民到这条溪流
It's a tiny goby and it's a rock climber.
小虾虎鱼，攀岩高手
With pelvic fins fused into a disc, which acts like a sucker,
它的腹鳍呈盘状，像个吸盘
all the goby needs is a film of water to climb through.
小虾虎鱼只需爬过一层薄的“水墙”
The pioneer is soon followed by many others,
先锋不一会儿就被其它的追随
possibly following its scent trail.
可能是沿着它的气味
They clamber on, ever upwards against the flow.
它们逆着水流向上爬行
Drops of water fall like bombs.
水滴下来如同炸弹
False leads waste crucial energy.
失误会导致体力的浪费
Some must rest.
有些需要休息
For others, the effort is just too much.
另一些，消耗太多
Many die in their attempt to reach to top.
会在半路上死掉
Against all the odds a few heroic individuals do make it to the top.
尽管困难重重，还是有少数能英雄般地到达上面
They find themselves in a near-perfect fish habitat...
它们为自己找到了一个近乎完美的栖息地
..where the gobies can feed and grow and breed in peace.
在那儿，小虾虎鱼能够安宁地生长、繁衍
In time their own young will be swept downstream and out to sea
最后，它们的后代会被水流冲走，到达大海
and the cycle will begin all over again.
然后开始新一轮的循环
Fresh water presents particular challenges for fish.
淡水给鱼类带来了特殊的挑战
Nutrients can be in very short supply in spring water,
春天的淡水中，营养非常稀少
so here fish must take every chance they can to find food.
所以要找到食物，必须把握住每一个机会
The rain that falls on these Kenyan hills percolates through the rocks.
雨水落到肯尼亚山上，从岩石中渗出来
Finally emerging as crystal clear pools.
最终形成一个个清澈的水池
Pools that are home to fish including barbel.
是很多鱼类的家，包括鱼
The fish share these waters with all sorts of creatures...
鱼和很多其它的生物在此共存
..including hippopotamus.
包括河马
These giant vegetarians are no threat to the fish,
这些巨大的素食者对鱼类没有威胁
in fact they're key to their survival here.
事实上，它们是鱼儿在此生存的关键
After a night of grazing on land, these hippos return
河马们经过陆地上一夜的饱餐
to spend the daylight hours in the cooling waters.
返回到凉爽的水塘里呆上几小时
And the barbel come to meet them.
鱼们前来迎接
Soon each hippo is trailed by a shoal of fish,
每头河马身后一下子就跟来一群鱼
waiting for their breakfast.
等待着开饭呢
Hippo droppings.
河马排便
But it's not just the hippo's dung the fish are interested in.
但鱼对河马的粪便并不感兴趣
When the hippos reach one particular spot in the pool,
当河马来到水池里合适的地点后
they stand still and wait.
它们便站着不动，等待
And the fish start to clean them...
鱼们开始清除它们身上的
..removing ticks, parasites and other tasty morsels.
虱子、寄生虫以及可口的碎屑
To the fish the hippos are a mobile cafeteria.
对鱼来说，河马就像是个移动餐厅
The hippos seem to be enjoying the sensation.
河马们看起来很享受呢
The only thing that interrupts the feast
唯一能打断这场宴会的
is the need to take an occasional breath.
是河马必须浮出水面呼吸
Cleaning the hippo's skin was just the hors d'oeuvre.
给河马清洁皮肤只是开胃菜
Now it's time for the main course.
现在到了正餐环节
So, in addition to providing skin care,
所以，除了帮助治疗皮肤病
the fish look after the hippos' dental hygiene.
鱼还是河马的口腔医生
It's an arrangement that suits both parties.
这种方式对双方都有利
But perhaps it is the fish that are the overall winners.
但有可能鱼们获利更多
For, thanks to the hippos, they are able to feed on
因为，在河马的帮助下
the abundant vegetation that would otherwise be beyond their reach,
它们能吃到那些本来遥不可及的
growing around their pool, on land.
生长在水池旁边陆地上的东西
Providing a cleaning service is clearly a good way of getting a meal.
很明显，提供清洁服务是混口饭吃的好办法
And there is cleaning to be done in the sea as well.
在海洋里，也有时需要清理服务
The life of this wrasse is centred on removing parasites from other reef fish...
这种濑鱼的生活主要集中于清除其它鱼身上的寄生虫
..including predatory jacks.
包括"食肉杰克"（译者自命名）
Normally they would snap up such a little fish,
通常他们能一口吞下这样的小鱼
but this is an established relationship
但它们有明确的关系
and both sides know the rules.
双方都明白游戏规则
With so many jacks and only a few wrasse in attendance,
由于食肉杰克太多，而濑鱼很少
not all the jacks are going to get cleaned.
并非所有的都能得到清理
But all this life attracts other predators.
这里的生物也引来了其它猎食者
Silvertip sharks.
银鲨
The reef provides shelter for the smaller fish,
珊瑚礁能给小鱼提供庇护
but the jacks remain exposed.
食肉杰克依然暴露
Yet this may be a chance
这样或许有了机会
for the jacks to solve their cleaning problem.
食肉杰克们可以解决清理问题
They've spotted an opportunity.
T它们觅得时机
Sharks have skin like sand paper.
银鲨的皮肤就像砂纸
And bumping into the sharks' flanks
从鲨鱼的侧边撞过去
helps the jacks to rid themselves of parasites and dead skin.
能够帮助食肉杰克清除掉身上的寄生虫和死皮
Perhaps the jacks find this a more effective alternative to the cleaner fish.
也许它们发现这种清洁方法比濑鱼还要有效
And soon swarms of jacks pursue the sharks.
不久就有一群食肉杰克尾随着鲨鱼
All itching to have a scratch.
都跑过来蹭几下痒痒
Unsurprisingly all this attention bothers the sharks
这种行为无疑让鲨鱼很烦恼
and they head back to the blue water,
它们掉头游向深水区
leaving the residents of the reef to resume life as normal.
使得珊瑚礁居民的生活回复了宁静
Coral reefs are the richest habitats on Earth.
珊瑚礁是地球上最富饶的生物栖息地
It's not surprising that,
毫不意外的是
with so many different kinds of animals living so closely together,
这么多种不同动物紧密地生活在一起
some extraordinary relationships have evolved.
必然会演化出一些特殊的种间关系
A clownfish, a small and defenceless resident of the reef.
小丑鱼，没有自卫能力的珊瑚礁居民
It seems to have picked a tough place to live,
看起来选了个糟糕的生活场所
amongst the tentacles of a sea anemone.
在海葵的触手之间
Each tentacle is armed with paralysing stings that can kill a fish.
每支触手都有毒刺，可以杀死一条鱼
Yet the clown fish are totally immune.
但小丑鱼完全不受影响
For this pair, the anemone is like a castle.
这一组合，海葵就像城堡
So long as they stay surrounded by the tentacles, they're safe
只要它们呆在海葵周围，就很安全
and so this is where they choose to lay their eggs.
它们也在这里产卵
After carefully selecting the site,
经过仔细的地点选择
work begins on preparing the surface.
它们开始清扫表面
Both fish share in the labour,
两条鱼分担工作
though it's the larger female who decides when all is ready.
然后由较大的雄鱼决定是否就绪
Lines and lines of tiny eggs are stuck to the rock and then fertilised.
一行行的小鱼卵被黏附在岩石上，然后受精
They're laid so close to the anemone they will be safe.
这些卵很靠近海葵，所以比较安全
And for the next seven days they'll receive constant care...
接下来的七天，它们会得到始终如一的照顾
..much of which is provided by the male.
大部分来自鱼爸爸
His seemingly obsessive concern for the eggs is for good reason.
它看起来如此担心那些卵，是有原因的
His position in the anemone is far from secure.
鱼卵在海葵丛中并不十分安全
The female watches his every move,
雌鱼关注着它的一举一动
she's in charge here and if his efforts don't match up
她掌控着这里，如果雄鱼的努力不符合她的要求
to her standards, she'll get rid of him.
她就会赶走他
In line to take over are a host of immature clown fish...
排队候补的是一群半大的小丑鱼
..each waiting to move up the hierarchy.
每一个都伺机取而代之
For the male the best way to stay in the female's favour
对雄鱼来说，得到雌鱼偏爱的最好方法
is by lavishing care on the eggs.
就是好好照顾鱼卵
So he focuses all his efforts on keeping them clean and healthy.
所以它集中精力，使它们保持清洁、健康
The eggs grow rapidly and soon their tiny beating hearts are visible.
卵发育很快，不久就能看见它们跳动的小心脏
It seems he's done a good job.
看起来它干得不错
Clown fish can hide away within an anemone.
小丑鱼可以躲进海葵里休息了
But most fish don't have this option.
但大多数的鱼没这个办法
For some, the only way of avoiding danger
有一些，它们逃离危险的唯一途径
is by hiding amongst their own kind...
就是躲进一大群
..in shoals.
同类中
Packed close together, no one anchovy stands out.
尽管很挤，但没一条凤尾鱼跑出来
By sensing and reacting to the movements
通过感官对同伴的行动做出迅速反应
of their immediate neighbours, thousands can move as one.
它们可以做到“千鱼一律”
For a predator, picking out an individual becomes nearly impossible.
对捕食者来说，从中挑出一条，几乎是不可能的
The shoal's unity is its strength.
团结就是力量
Yet each fish is acting from selfish motives.
尽管每条鱼的动机都是利己的
Moving together, the fish confuse the sea lions so much
通过整体行动，鱼群使得海狮如此迷惑
that they leave to look elsewhere for a smaller, less tricky target.
它们只得离开，去别处寻找小的、不这么狡猾的目标
The sheer size of the shoal defeated the sea lions,
鱼群整体击败了海狮
but there are fish that can overcome such strategies.
但有的鱼可以挫败这种战术
Off the coast of South Africa
南非海域
this huge shoal of sardines is shadowed by a ragged tooth shark.
这群沙丁鱼被一条锯齿鲨尾随
Other sharks join the menacing escort.
其它鲨鱼也加入了“护航”
The shoal has been driven into the shallows by a cold ocean current.
这群鱼被一股冷流逼进了浅水区
And this gives the sharks an opportunity.
这就给了鲨鱼们机会
Hundreds have moved into position.
几百条鲨鱼就位
Sharks have a special sense, they can detect
鲨鱼有特殊的感官，能侦测出
the electrical signals their prey gives off when it moves.
猎物移动时发出的电信号
It's a sixth sense that can give them an edge.
这就是使它们占优势的第六感
But with hundreds of thousands of fish crammed into the shallows,
但现在成千上万条鱼挤在浅水区
the sharks now need only rely on their speed and agility.
鲨鱼就只能依靠自己的速度和敏捷
As the first shark starts to hunt in earnest,
一旦第一条鲨鱼开始认真捕猎
a feeding frenzy breaks out.
一场狂乱的盛宴爆发了
The shoal's defences are weakened,
鱼群的防线开始削弱
there isn't enough space to manoeuvre.
这里没有足够的空间来迂回
And the sharks can gorge themselves.
鲨鱼可以吞下它们
Despite the casualties,
尽管伤亡很多
the shoal is so vast that the sharks have little effect on its size.
但鱼群太过庞大，鲨鱼造成的影响其实非常微小
Fish not only come together in great shoals for defence,
鱼类不仅以群体方式进行防御
but at other critical times in their lives,
还会在生命中的另一些关键时刻
when they're ready to spawn.
比如它们排卵
These events only occur for a few days each year.
这事情只会发生在每年的那几天
Snapper are normally solitary, but they've travelled here
真鳍蓝雕通常独立生活，但它们从伯利兹城海岸
from hundreds of miles away to gather off the coast of Belize.
远道而来，聚集在一起
Along this one reef, cubera, dog and mutton snapper form huge shoals.
沿着这块礁石，真鳍蓝雕形成一个巨大的群体
60 metres down, there is an eerie coolness to the scene.
60米水下，有着阴森、冰冷的感觉
But things are about to hot up.
但马上就要热闹起来
It's the evening of the full moon, the tides are just right.
月圆之夜，潮水刚好
A great column of fish leaves the bottom.
一大群鱼从海底蹿升
As they rise through the water, small groups break free of the shoal.
上升途中，一小部分从鱼群中冲出
Each burst is led by a female, with the males racing behind.
雌鱼在前排卵，雄鱼在后面紧追
As she sheds her eggs, they add their sperm to the mix.
排出卵后，雄鱼将精子与之混合
By synchronising the time when they gather together,
由于它们聚集时已同期发情
the maximum numbers of fish can join in this mass spawning.
产卵时，参与的鱼能够达到最大数量
Millions of fertilized eggs are released,
数百万的受精卵被释放
cast into the ocean currents...
汇入了洋流
..and straight into a dangerous world.
直接进入危险的世界
Whale sharks, the largest fish on Earth.
鲸鲨，地球上最大的鱼
Each shark might weigh ten tonnes
每一条鲸鲨可重达10吨
yet they feed on the tiniest creatures, including snapper eggs.
但它们却吃极为微小的生物，如真鳍蓝雕的卵
Life is being created, sustained and destroyed simultaneously
生命的被创造、延续、被消灭
in one huge event.
在一次大事件里同时发生
The struggle for life, encapsulated into a single moment.
生存斗争，全都浓缩在了这一时刻
The oceans are perilous places to live,
海洋是危险的生存之地
yet fish have developed the most extraordinary means for survival.
鱼类已进化出非常特殊的方法以求生存
Their astounding diversity, the product of millions of years
它们惊人的多样性，亿万年的进化成果
of evolution, has enabled them to triumph.
使它们获得成功
Dominating the one habitat that we have so far failed to make our own.
统治着目前我们自己还无法占据的栖息地
Filming under water raised all sorts of problems for the Life team.
水下拍摄给Life制作组带来了各种各样的困难
Not least of which was that they were only able to experience
他们在氧气瓶里的气体用完之前
the underwater world for as long as the air on their backs or in their lungs held out.
只能短暂体验一下这个水下世界
But over three years the team were lucky enough to capture on film
但三年来，制作组非常有幸地拍下了
some extraordinary moments in the lives of fish.
一些鱼类非同寻常的精彩瞬间
The waters off the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico
墨西哥尤卡坦半岛海域
are a rich hunting ground for Sailfish.
是旗鱼富饶的猎食场所
Cameraman Rick Rosenthal
摄影师Rick Rosenthal
has teamed up with sport fishing Captain Anthony Mendillo
和海钓队长Anthony Mendillo合作
to try and film the hunting behaviour of these amazing animals.
试图拍下这些奇异生物的猎食场面
It's fish!
鱼来了！
Feeding birds lead them to the sailfish.
食鱼鸟带领他们找到了旗鱼
Right here.Right here.
在这儿，在这儿呢
Getting to the bait balls and into the water quickly is key,
在它们的宴会结束前，快速赶到并且下水
before the feast is consumed.
是非常关键的
Get ready.
准备
Everybody hang on.
都抓紧了！
Let's go swimming, now, now.
我们下水吧，下，下
Go on get in there.
去那里
It's all very well telling Rick to hurry
让Rick赶快是没错的
but these fish are capable of swimming at over 60 miles an hour.
这群鱼能游出时速60英里以上
Just keeping up with them is hard enough.
想跟上它们非常困难
Getting right in amongst the action is vital,
正好进入它们中间是很必要的
but Rick has to try to avoid becoming part of it.
但是Rick还必须尽量不要打扰到它们
Bills nearly one metre long, scything through the water at break neck speed
体长接近一米，以刀锋一样的速度破水前进
are guaranteed to get the heart racing.
是极速竞赛的保证
But Rick holds his nerve
Rick绷紧神经
as the sailfish pick off sardine after sardine right in front of him.
旗鱼在他面前逐一地干掉一条条的沙丁鱼
Almost as soon as it started, it was all over.
就在这一切开始时，就差不多结束了
That was a wild feed show out there today.
今天这真是一场野性的盛宴
Really wild.
非常狂野
Must have been 50 sailfish if there was...
那里应该有50条旗鱼
Or 49, but very aggressive fish, very hungry, everybody on the move
49条吧，非常具有侵略性，极度饥饿，每条都在行动
and I had to just keep kicking and kicking and kicking
我必须不停地把摄影机转啊，转啊，转啊……
and kicking and kicking and kicking to keep in the action,
以便跟上节奏
because after a while the sardine patch was eaten up
因为不一会儿，沙丁鱼就被吃光了
to just a little sliver and then it was over.
只剩下一些残肢碎片，结束了
Nearly 2,000 miles away on the other side of the Caribbean
在加勒比海另一边2000英里外
another crew is taking a slightly different approach.
另一小组正在进行另一种拍摄
They are trying to film flying fish.
他们打算拍摄飞鱼
The team sets out at dawn on the Hog Snapper, a commercial fishing boat.
摄制组在拂晓时乘Hog Snapper号渔船出发
Conditions are in stark contrast to the gleaming sport fishing boat in Mexico.
这里的条件比墨西哥那边的渔船要糟糕的多
There's Doug he's ready for action, look.
这是Doug，他准备好了，看
They are hoping to use a local fisherman's expertise to put them in the right place at the right time.
他们希望借助本地人的经验，将他们适时地带到合适的地点
Yeah, Roger that. All you catching there's food.
是，收到，你们那里有食物
You catching dinner, lunch and breakfast.
晚餐、午餐和早餐
It's not a big boat and the crew's bedroom has now become the kitchen.
这只船不大，组员的卧室现在成了厨房
We're having fried bacon and fried egg this morning.
今天早餐你们吃煎咸肉和煎鸡蛋
Fried bacon and fried eggs.
煎咸肉和煎鸡蛋
I'm the trainee chef and I don't...
我受过厨师训练……
So I don't get to wear the white wellies.
所以我不必要穿白色雨靴
Rather than racing around the ocean chasing the action,
与其在海面上到处追寻它们
the flying fish team have to sit it out
飞鱼摄制组干脆
and wait for the fish to come to them.
坐等飞鱼来找他们
Flying fish will spawn onto debris in the water
飞鱼在水里是分散生活的
and the team tie on to a floating palm frond
组员们绑了根棕榈叶在船后
to try and make sure they're close by in case the action begins.
确保飞鱼们会聚集着跟过来
And sure enough, they don't have long to wait.
果然，他们没等太久
Thousands of fish have massed below the surface,
水面下聚集了成千上万条飞鱼
all intent on reaching the frond.
它们都在追逐棕榈叶
And the frond is not the only thing
飞鱼们并不只是将卵排到棕榈叶上
that they're trying to lay their eggs on.
（还弄到摄影师身上）
The weight of the eggs sinks the palm frond
鱼卵的重量将叶子压沉
and puts an end to the spawning and to the crew's filming.
然后产卵结束，拍摄工作也结束了
Well, it's moments like that we do the job for.
好了，看起来这就是我们想要的
Everything was right.
一切顺利
The light was right, blue water,
光线好，蓝色的水
the four tonnes of flying fish all going mental.
四吨多的飞鱼都发狂了
Thanks, Barry.You're welcome.
多谢，Barry     别客气
But now the fish's attention is turned to something bigger.
但现在，飞鱼的注意力转向了更大的家伙
Their spawning directly onto the boat.
它们直接朝船上排卵
Barry is worried as he drags up a huge sheet of eggs.
Barry很担心，提起了一大片鱼卵
Gotta bring it on the boat and check it out.
得把它弄起来，查看一下
I cleaned this off like five minutes a go. Right?
我五分钟前已经把这个清理干净了，对吧
Right now the problem is this, there's too many flying fish...
现在的问题是，这里的飞鱼太多了
Too many...around us.
太多了，我们周围
If we moor through the nights with the lights on and stuff,
如果我们在这里抛锚过夜，灯开着
more and more will keep coming and what they're doing is they're actually laying on the boat now,
会引来越来越多的飞鱼，它们会将卵排在船体上
so the boat has become their object and that is not good.
就是说船将成为它们的目标，这可不妙
So basically you're worried that if we just stay on this drift
简单的说，你是在担心，如果我们呆在这里
we're gonna sink the boat.
船可能会沉
Five hours from now that'll 3,000 pounds.Yeah, yeah.
五小时后，是的，船后面会增重3000磅
In the back here, it will sink the boat.
这会把船弄沉的
OK, so we've got to leave this area.
好的，我们得离开这里
Yeah, we can't stay here.
是的，此地不宜久留
Just five minutes of spawning has produced this.
仅仅五分钟，就产了这么多卵
The team have no option but to move on.
制作组没得选择，只能撤
The next day the search for flying fish begins all over again.
接着的一天，得又一次地寻找飞鱼
This time the team want to film the fish doing what they're famous for.
这一次，制作组想拍摄飞鱼们最有名的行为
We've got some lovely shots from the spawning
我们已经拍到了它们产卵的精彩画面
but now the really hard bit of trying to get them flying.
现在，真正的难点是让它们飞起来
Gonna be, gonna be a good challenge.
将会是很好的挑战
The fish are around, but they're all too far off to film.
鱼就在周围，但对拍摄来说太远了
The action is impressive this morning,
它们今早的行为令人印象深刻
unpredictable but impressive but it's distant,
捉摸不定，很难忘，但是太远了
it's not happening next to the boat today.
并不在船附近
They're either being chased off or they're just not interested. Look!
它们要么是被追赶，要么是随意的，看！
Look, look! Ah it's loads.
看，都跳起来了
The next day the crew decides to try a different approach.
接下来一天，组员们决定用别的方法
All right, lets go.
好了，我们走吧
Now they're just where they need to be,
现在他们到了目的地
but it puts them directly in the firing line.
但正好处在了火线上
I guess that's one!
我猜是这只
Despite being bombarded, their strategy is paying off.
尽管被撞到，他们的策略是值得的
That was amazing, we spent a long time in that wee boat today. Thanks.
太奇妙了，我们在小船上呆了很长时间
But the last two hours were just off the scale.
最后的两小时，我们都累了
We were just getting shot after shot. We need...
我们被一次又一次地撞上
Can't wait to watch it on the big monitor but it felt really good.
等不及去大的监视器上观看，但感觉好极了
And Doug is right,
Doug说的对
it worked.
成功了
Flying fish taking to the air and flying.
飞鱼飞到了空中
Slowed down 40 times.
放慢40倍
By working with people more used to catching fish than filming them
通过和经常捕鱼的人合作
the Life team have been able to gain a unique insight
Life制作组能以一个独特的视角
into the hidden world of fish.
探知鱼类的隐秘世界
For your free Open University Tree of Life poster call...
生命进化史函授海报上的免费电话
..or visit the website.
或登陆我们的网站